# 这个菜是我第一次吃
It is my first time eating this dish.
# 浓眉大眼 老菜
Big eyes and bushy eyebrows. An old dish.
# 象眼鸽蛋
Pigeon eggs in the elephant eyes.
# 边要去掉 边要不去掉
The frame of bread must be cut out, if not,
# 这菜我太有印象了
# 它炸完了以后上色
This dish impressed me.
the bread frame will be colored after fried.
# 73年我上服装学校的时候
When I was in a clothing school in 1973,
# 我们的老师 （教）宫廷的
our teacher taught us the dishes in the court,
# 他曾经教过这个菜 叫象眼鸽蛋
he taught me this dish, named Pigeon Eggs in Elephant Eyes,
# 所以说到今天我记忆犹新
so until today it remained fresh in my memory.
# 然后这个菜现在市面没有了看不到了
But this dish has disappeared in today’s market.
# 大爷今天重新给再现
Da Ye wants to reproduce it today.
# 这个菜其实我要重点的说一说
I have to emphasize this dish.
# 它这个面包炸出来很酥 虾又香
The bread after fried is very crispy, and the shrimp also smells great.
# 过去的老菜 它确实你得继承
You have to inherit the old dish.
# 为什么说要继承传统文化啊
That’s why we talk about inheriting the traditional culture.
# 菱形 象眼么
The rhombus, the elephant eyes.
# 大象的眼睛 象形
It is like the eyes of the elephants.
# 切下来的面包 切成粒儿
Cut the bread frame into small pieces,
# 面包鱼排 鸡排 虾排 肉排都可以
and you can use it to make bread fish steak, chicken steak, shrimp steak, or pork steak,
# 一点不浪费
so that you don’t waste it.
# 大爷您这肯定这个菜没少做啊
Da Ye, you must had made this dish very often.
# 那阵是这样
True, in the old days.
# 比如这道菜一卖就卖一星期
For example, this dish was sold for a week,
# 熟悉下来以后 会干了要精干
after you get familiar with the process, you need to refine your skill,
# 精干了还要快干巧干 这是一功夫菜
and after you refine your skill, you still need to find ways to make it quickly and effortlessly, so it is a dish that needs a lot of efforts.
# 好了 齐了
Alright.
# 蘸干（虾仁）水分
Soak up the water (in the shrimp).
# 一拍 剁成虾蓉 虾腻子
Pat it to make shrimp paste.
# 过去由于内地没有大虾 全是小虾
Because in the old days the mainland China only had small shrimps, no big shrimps,
# 但是小虾你要是炒个虾仁
but if you make a fried small shrimp,
# 它不算大菜
it is not a big dish,
# 所以用这虾仁把它做成馅
so we make the shrimp into shrimp paste,
# 再给它变成大菜
and then make it into a big dish.
# 烧点水一会烫烫桃仁
Heat up some water to soak the walnut kernel later.
# 来点肥膘
Let’s get some fat pork.
# 肥膘最好的是通脊肉底下那块肥膘
The best fat pork is the fat lining under the tenderloin.
# 这个肥膘我们要切薄一点的话
If we cut the fat pork thinly,
# 拿开水一烫 这肥膘吃起来是脆的
and soak it with boiling water, it will taste crispy.
# 一斤虾二两肥膘
1 jin (500g) shrimp with 2 liang (300g) fat pork.
# 这口感好
It tastes great.
# 刀背砸一砸
Use the back of the knife to pat it.
# 砸到最好效果是什么 起毛
What is the best result of patting? It fluffs.
# 看这桃仁没有
Look at these walnut kernels,
# 桃仁有这外皮特别涩 烫一下
the crusts of the walnut kernels taste puckery, let’s soak them with boiling water.
# 这是老桃仁 必须用老桃仁
These are old walnut kernels, we must use old walnut kernels.
# 嫩桃仁油性低 它不香
The young walnut kernels contain little oil, so they smell not that good.
# 来咱们做这虾馅
Let’s make the shrimp filling.
# 葱姜酒水把它捏一捏 出点味 就够了
Pinch the green onions and ginger so that they have some taste in the wine water, that’s enough.
# 然后我们搁点盐
Then let’s add some salt,
# 淀粉 玉米淀粉
starch, corn starch,
# 白胡椒粉
white pepper,
# 蛋清 有半个蛋清
egg white, half egg white.
# 这馅儿一打得了 这菜就完成大半了
Let’s temper the filling, and the dish is already mostly finished.
# 看看 上劲了 颤嘟嘟的
Look, it is cohesive.
# 有弹性
# 上劲儿它才成型
It is resilient.
It has to be cohesive to make shapes.
# 咱们现在剥桃仁 以半个为单位
Let’s peel the walnut kernels in the unit of half of the kernels.
# 这皮不去掉 它吃起来有点涩苦
If the crusts are not peeled, they will taste a little bitter.
# 这个在这个菜里边像不像大象的眉毛
Is this seemed like the eyebrows of elephants in this dish?
# 给点油 炸桃仁 这活就差不多了
Add some oil and fry the walnut kernels, then this dish is almost done.
# 面包上的要搁上点干淀粉 玉米淀粉
Add some starch and corn starch to the bread,
# 搁这个就为了馅不跟面包分离
so that the filling will not separate with the bread,
# 才能锁得住
and the filling is sticked.
# 再拍拍 瓤馅的东西都要拍粉
Pat it, all the things with fillings must have starch.
# 鸽蛋太贵了
Pigeon eggs are too expensive,
# （一个鸽蛋）快顶一斤鸡蛋了
(one pigeon egg) worths 1 jin (500g) chicken eggs.
# 桃仁好了 炸一下
The walnut kernels are done, let’s fry them
# 凉油 小火慢炸
Cool oil, soft fire to fry them slowly,
# 轻轻上一点点颜色就好了
and color it slightly.
# 细致活
A careful piece of work.
# 亮子看见了吗 蘸点粉子
Liang Zi, did you see? Add some starch.
# 我们开始给它抹
Let’s put the filling
# 把虾馅抹在面包上
on the bread,
# 而且要包着鸽蛋（鹌鹑蛋）
and make sure the filling is around the “pigeon egg” (quail egg),
# 不然的话就掉了
or the quail egg will fall.
# 好了这菜就完事了
Alright, this dish is done.
# 说这形状像大象眼睛
This shape is like the eyes of the elephants.
# 这桃仁炸完了以后有油
The walnut kernels after fried are oily,
# 不爱粘 给它裹点淀粉
so it is not sticky. Let’s wrap them with starch.
# 大象的眉毛眼儿 眼角 就完事了
The eyebrows and the corners of the elephants’ eyes, then it is done!
# 粘个香菜 浓眉大眼
Let’s stick a cilantro leaf, big eyes with bushy eyebrows.
# 好了这就烧油了
Alright, let’s heat up oil.
# 肉朝下 肉厚 把肉炸熟了 五成
The filling side is down. The filling is thick. Make sure it is fully cooked. 150 centigrade.
# 下这个也是一个技术活 溜锅边儿下
It needs skills to put the dish into the pot. Stick it with the pot.
# 炸熟 把这面包炸成金黄色
Fully fried it, colored the bread yellow.
# 好了 就这么快
Alright, it is very quick!
# 这个菜我是第一次吃
It is my first time having this dish,
# 这个做法我也是第一次见着
and it is also my first time to see this process.
# 说这样做出来的菜
This dish made of this process,
# 这个菜要让我吃这一盘
I can eat them all
# 一个人正好
Just enough for only one person
# 品尝桃仁的香 鹌鹑蛋的香
Taste the great smells of the walnut kernels and the quail eggs,
# 加上虾的香 再加上面包的酥脆
plus the shrimp and the crispy bread
# 二伯尝尝
Er Bai, have a try
# 这回该您说了
Time for you to say something
# 你说过去的传统菜确实讲究
You know, the traditional dishes are really deliberate.
# 大人小孩都能吃
Both children and adults can eat it.
# 我们要做宴会
If we are going to make a banquet,
# 也是一道非常经典的老菜
this is also a very classical traditional dish,
# 依然能放出光彩来
and it must be great.
# 手打牛肉丸叫濑尿牛丸
Handmade beef balls are called Lai Niao beefballs
# 是吧
Yeah
# 有什么技巧吗
Is there any skills,
# 才能把这牛肉丸打的
to make the beefballs
# 就真能扔地上就弹起来
can even bounce from the floor?
# 首先我们就选精制的瘦牛肉
Firstly, we should choose the thin beef,
# 放在墩子上
put it on a block of wood.
# 用刀背先把它砸成粗蓉
Use the back of knife to beat it into rough paste,
# 再拿那擀面杖
and then use the rolling pin,
# 或者是木棒子
or wood stick,
# 也是硬一点的
something solid,
# 一点一点的砸
to beat it slowly.
# 砸的时候
When you beat the beef,
# 一定要把这肉泥砸的特别细
you must make it into fine paste.
# 得拉黏儿是吧
It should have wires right?
# 拉黏
Yes, wires,
# 或者说很粘稠
or very cohesive.
# 后边我们就开始打牛肉丸
Then let’s make the beef balls.
# 我们在打馅的时候
When we make the paste,
# 除了放葱姜酒水
besides the wine water of green onions and ginger,
# 还要少放一点食用碱的碱水
We also need some water with little alkali,
# 然后放盐
and then add some salt
# 根据自己喜欢的口味
based on your taste,
# 比如胡椒
For example, some pepper,
# 略微要放一点蛋清
a little bit egg white,
# 少加一点点淀粉或者生粉
a little bit starch or corn starch.
# 然后我们挤肉丸儿
Then let’s make the balls.
# 它有碱水的这个过程
It has alkali water,
# 牛肉丸出来以后
so, when the beef ball is made out,
# 它就富有弹性
it will be elastic.
# 加碱水就能富有弹性
Adding some alkali water will make it elastic
# 大概加多少
Approximately how much should we add?
# 二斤肉丸吧
2 jin (1000g) beef balls,
# 比如说5克或者3克
for example, 5g or 3g.
# 第一你可以试
Firstly, you can try.
# 比如我先搁3克
For example, I firstly add 3g,
# 你看打完了
after the beef balls are made,
# 挤出一个丸子搁这水
put one in the water,
# 汆熟的时候你看效果
fully cook it to see the result.
# 不够弹力
If it is not elastic enough,
# 还要再加上2克
add 2g more.
# 可以现加是吧
So we can add the alkali water then?
# 但是现加以后
But after adding the alkali water,
# 一定要给它一定的时间
you must give it some time,
# 比如还有可能还要加一点点的小苏打
for example, it is possible that it still needs a little baking soda,
# 使它能嫩
so that it is soft and tender.
# 明白
Got it.
# 敲牛肉的时候要敲多长时间
How long should we beat the beef?
# 应该说要敲到两个小时左右
Approximately two hours
# 不是说像我们买的肉馅
It is impossible that the chopped beef that we buy
# 就能打成那样肉丸那是不可能的
can be made into beef balls.
# 敲的时候要着实的敲
When beating the beef, you must beat it powerfully.
# 别用这棒子尖
Don’t use the sharp side of the stick,
# 老是砸一坑不行
it is not ok to beat a pit.
# 千万不能用机器
Don’t use machines.
# 就完全要靠手工打
You must handmake it.
# 明白
Got you.
# 所以这是很要功夫的
So it needs a lot of efforts.
# 所以说总结技巧的话就是两点
So I conclude two skills.
# 一是功夫
One is effort,
# 就是要敲打两个小时
Which means you must beat it two hours,
# 对吧
right?
# 匀速
In a constant speed.
# 然后像刚才您说那个技巧
And like the skill you said
# 另外一个就是加碱水
The other skill is to add some alkali water,
# 加以适当的加一点碱水不要多
add a little bit alkali water, don’t add too much.
# 那个碱水是什么呢
What is that alkali water?
# 这点呢要讲一个我们传统的工艺
Here we need to talk about one of our traditional technique.
# 比如过去我们做水晶虾
For example, in the past we made crystal shrimp.
# 由于过去在70年代
Because in the 70s,
# 物产不发达
products are not very abundant,
# 很多大虾都在一个冷库里边
many big shrimps are in a refrigeration storage,
# 而且不是超低温冷库
and were not even ultralow refrigerator,
# 基本上都是零下6度最低的也就12度
mostly -6 centigrade, the lowest was -12 centigrade.
# 虾由于长时间的保存
The shrimps were not very fresh
# 这虾就不是很新鲜了
because of longtime storage,
# 但是我们这虾还要用
but we still needed to use the shrimps,
# 有的还变色了
some of the shrimps even changed color,
# 变成红色了
turned into red.
# 像这种虾可能要炒着吃
The shrimps like that sometimes were going to be fried,
# 做馅都不行了
but not for making fillings.
# 所以我们在腌制这虾的时候
So, when we cured the shrimps,
# 要搁点食用碱
we needed to add some dietary alkali
# 拿它一下
to cure it.
# 等拿完了以后
After curing,
# 再把这碱水再给它冲出去
the alkali water needed to be washed out.
# 你再看这虾
Then you looked at the shrimp,
# 那虾就透明的
it became transparent.
# 当然说我们还有好多工业上的
Of course, we have a lot of industrial,
# 食品工业当中的一些添加剂
additive in food industry.
# 因为咱们在民间的生活当中
Because in our daily life,
# 我们很少用
we seldom use,
# 基本就用一点碱水
basically only use a little bit alkali water.
# 还有像南方的广东那边
And like Guangdong Province in the south,
# 专门有一种
There is a special
# 做菜用的碱水
Alkali water for cuisine,
# 这个是可以用的
and that is good to use.
# 就做这种手打牛肉丸
For making the handmade beef balls,
# 最好是选择什么牛的什么部位
What part of beef should we choose?
# 牛肉丸 一般就是用后腿
Beef balls usually are made of round flank,
# 就纯瘦肉
pure thin beef.
# 我们打完了以后
After we make it,
# 拿水汆得了
fully cook it with boiling water,
# 往地下一扔
and throw it on the floor,
# 能蹦起一米高以上
it can bounce to 1m or higher.
# 您做过
You have made it?
# 我曾经打过
Yes, I had.
# 因为我们原来碰到这些学校
Because the schools we met
# 说这牛肉丸怎么打完了也不脆
said the beef balls were not crispy,
# 很简单
it is actually very simple,
# 就是搁点碱
just to add some alkali.
# 以前因为我们不注重食品安全
In the past we didn’t care much about food safety,
# 像他们民间还会搁点火碱
sometimes people even add some caustic soda.
# 现在是绝对不能用
Now it is prohibited to use that.
# 现在我们可以略微搁一点食用碱
Now we can add a little dietary alkali.
# 好的
Ok.
# 是可以用的
It can be used.
# 好勒
# 好谢谢
Alright.
Ok, thank you!